Exercise 4-2, Betty bought a bit of better butter. In the sentence, Betty bought a
bit of better butter, all the t's are in weak positions, so they all sound like
soft d's. Repeat the sentence slowly, word by word. Betty bought a bit of better
butter. Feel the tip of your tongue flick across that area behind your top teeth.
Think of the music of a cello again when you say, Betty bought a bit of better
butter. Betty bought a bit of better butter. But, said she, this butter's
bitter. If I put it in my batter, it'll make my batter bitter. If you speak any
language, such as Spanish, Japanese, Hindi, Italian, or Dutch, among others,
where your R touches behind the teeth, you're in luck with the American T. Just
fix the association in your mind so that when you see a middle-position T, you
automatically give it your native R sound. Say, Betty Bada Bida with your native
accent, not if you are French, German, or Chinese. Along with liaisons, the American
tea contributes a great deal to the smooth, relaxed sound of English. When you
say a word like Adam, imagine that you've been to the dentist and you're a little
numb or that you've had a couple of drinks, or maybe that you're very sleepy.
You won't be wanting to use a lot of energy saying Atom, so just relax
everything and say Adam. The masculine name Adam. It's a very smooth fluid sound.
Rather than saying Betty bought a bit of better butter, which is physically more
demanding, try Betty bought a bit of better butter. It's easy because you
really don't need much muscle tension to say it this way. The staircase concept
will help clarify the various T sounds. The American T can be a little tricky if
you base your pronunciation on spelling.